Today we are making raspberry gelato
with chocolate
fudge. When I grew up, raspberry ripple
was one of the most favored ice creams
around. And it's funny what your brain
does to memories. I remember it being
vanilla ice cream with a raspberry
ripple sauce through it. And that
raspberry ripple itself was super icy.
It was always icy. That was kind of the
point cuz it was a texture change in
that vanilla ice cream. And then someone
on social media said that it was
raspberry ice cream. Now, I don't I
don't know. In the UK, it was always
vanilla ice cream, but raspberry ice
cream kind of got my mouth watering. So,
what we're going to do today is just do
raspberry gelato. And in a future video,
we'll do raspberry ripple. Just hey, why
not? So, raspberry ice cream.
Raspberries are quite an acidic fruit
and they don't have huge amount of sugar
in them. So, we don't kind of have to
stress about that too much, but we do
need to make sure we balance it out. So,
it's pretty simple recipe. This for the
ice cream base. You are going to
need 170 g of fresh raspberries, 173 g
of cream, around 33% fat, 460 g of whole
milk. You can use 2% or semi-kinned
milk, that's fine, 70 gram of skim milk
powder, 172 g of sugar, and 10 g of
either dextrose, glucose, corn syrup, or
honey. One of those
four. That's it. Nice and easy. So,
first thing we're going to do is we're
going to get our raspberries and we're
going to just get them in a pan with our
sugar. and drop your raspberries. Now
into that we're going to add our sugar.
So 172 grams of
sugar. You can absolutely make this
sugar-free by using alos or xylitol etc.
Um if you use alulose you can pretty
much substitute this with sugar one to
one. If you use xylitol you're going to
have to drop that number down by about
30%. Anyway, with our raspberries and
our sugar in there, we're going to do
one little addition. And that is a
couple of tablespoons of water. That
addition of water, what it will do is it
will it will help the meration of the
actual raspberries and get those liquids
and those sugars out of there nice and
fast. So, let's pop that on the hob now.
And we're going to get the rest of our
ingredients ready.
So, 460 g of our milk, 173 g of our
cream, 70 g. So, periodically, we're
going to go back and stir your raspberry
sugar syrup. You're going to break those
raspberries down. It really won't take
long. It'll take
about 5 or 10 minutes for those
raspberries to completely break down and
that syrup to start bubbling. Dissipate
our milk powder. And we're going for 10
g. I'm going to use just straight corn
syrup like that. Like I said, you you
can use a variety of ingredients
um to do the same thing. So, with that
in there, we are going to get this on
the hob to nice and gentle heat because
what we're going to do is when our
raspberries are ready, we're going to
put that into this warm liquid. So,
straight onto the hob this goes. All
right. All right. So, our raspberries
just came up
to the first stages of a light boil and
we took it off the heat. What's happened
is the water has come out of that and
all the sugar has dissolved and that's
exactly what we're after. We're now
going to pop this into a little food
processor. Again, we're dealing with hot
ingredients, hot sugar. So, and the lid
is going to go on. And we're just going
to start pulsing that on low speed just
for 10 20
seconds. Perfect. We ran that on high
speed for about 10 15 seconds at the
end. So, we're going to bring our ice
cream base in here. It's not hot enough
yet, this, but what we're going to do is
we're going to get our really nice hot
raspberry syrup in here. Give that a
stir together. And out comes our really
nice soft pink color. If you want to add
some red food coloring to boost the
color, then by all means, you won't need
a lot. I'm not I'm going to keep it nice
and natural. So, now we're going to get
it back on hob. We're going to get this
up to about 50 to 60° centigrade. We
we've not using a stabilizer in this. We
don't need to heat it to any specific
temperature. I'm just bringing it up to
make sure all the fats, sugars, and
solids are emulsified together. So,
let's do that. Okay, that only took a
couple of minutes. Get it up to
temperature. Got it to the point where
the base starts to steam. So, that's
actually bang on between 50 and 60°
centigrade. That means evaporation
starting to take place. And we've burnt
off some of that water that we added to
our raspberries. It really doesn't take
a lot a long time to burn off 3
tablespoons of water. So, don't stress
about it. The rest will actually
evaporate off naturally as we cool it
down in the fridge. We're going to cool
it down over a period of time to let
those flavors completely bond together.
But one final thing we're going to do
here is add a tiny bit of vanilla
extract. We are literally only talking
about 2 to three grams. And that is to
help boost that raspberry flavor. So
there we go. Let's get it in a
container. Will it fit in this
one? I'm going to say
yes. And we're going to cool this down.
We will strain it before we churn it. In
the fridge just goes for about 4 hours
to let everything melt together. So
after it's all completely chilled down,
we're going to take a mesh strainer and
just run our base through there. There's
a lot of solids in this. So, um, we're
going to make sure we take out those
seeds and any other lumps. But
ultimately, it's pretty much just the
seeds left. Once you've strained it out,
we're going to pour it in your pre-
chilled ice cream machine. And I'm going
to use fudge. I've made this fudge a
lot. There's about 1.5 kilos of the
fudge here, which I keep in the freezer
downstairs. We're going to need about
100 g for this recipe. So, not knowing
what 100 g worth of homemade fudge looks
like, it was about 750 gram here. So,
let's cut a piece off and make sure that
we're using the right amount. And again,
the recipe for this fudge is linked
below. I've used it loads and loads of
varying recipes.
And 100 g. There are a few ways to deal
with the fudge here. You can use a
cheese grater, either side, or a knife.
I'm going to do both. So, this is going
to be the finer grating section of the
cheese grater. You need to work fast
with this fudge cuz it's going to melt
in your hands. It's designed to do that
so it doesn't go rock solid in your ice
cream. It's a really, really good fudge
and it tastes amazing if you just want
to eat it on its own, which I do. We're
also going to add in some slightly large
pieces just chopped up with a knife.
Now, as the ice cream is still churning,
we're going to pop our fudge in the
refrigerator just to harden back off for
about 5 or 10 minutes. And here we are
at the end of our churning phase. In
goes all the fudge. It's going to make a
mess. Don't stress about it.
And finally, we're going to dish up. And
I'm really kind of looking forward to
this. I haven't made a raspberry ice
cream for a long, long time. So, taking
it out the freezer. It looks great. It
smells great. And I can already tell
it's going to scoop perfectly. Look at
that. And loads of fudge pieces in here.
Really nice natural color here as well.
Let's get it on the spinny thing. Look
at that. It just looks delicious. So,
how did it turn out? Let's
see. Raspberry gelato with chocolate
fudge
pieces. Smells
delicious. It's got a lovely natural
raspberry flavor. Something to note,
raspberry ice cream and gelato that you
buy in almost all scoop shops. I've yet
to find one that does it like this, uses
raspberry extract because it's a much
much stronger flavor. It's something
along the lines of like banana ice
cream. They use banana extract, banana
flavoring to create banana ice cream.
And when you make a natural banana ice
cream, it's a totally different flavor
profile. And it takes a little bit, you
know, it takes a few seconds to get used
to it. That's the same with this. The
flavor is a natural raspberry flavor.
It's
delicious. Because we've made a gelato,
so something with
dairy, that raspberry flavor gets turned
into like um like a like I did with
strawberries before. Strawberries and
cream. This is like a raspberry and
cream kind of flavor. That fudge cuts
through as well for a change of texture
and a lovely delicious chocolate
fudgess. Super nice, refreshing at the
same
time. Lovely
texture, lovely
taste. I hope you give this one a try.
Raspberry is normally something that
just gets turned into sorbet, so turning
it into a gelato is quite unusual. So,
thanks very much for watching. Don't
forget to like and subscribe, and I'll
see you next week.
[Music]